<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ClinicalDocument xmlns="urn:hl7-org:v3">
  <title>Clinical Note - Pain Management Follow-up</title>
  <component>
    <structuredBody>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Chief Complaint</title>
          <text>
            <paragraph>Patient presents for follow-up of chronic low back pain with radiculopathy.</paragraph>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>History of Present Illness</title>
          <text>
            <paragraph>58-year-old male with chronic low back pain radiating to the left leg for the past 2 years.
            Patient reports pain level of 7/10 today, worse than previous visit. Pain is described as sharp,
            shooting down the posterior left thigh to the calf. Aggravated by prolonged sitting and standing.
            Partially relieved by lying down and heat application.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Patient has tried conservative management including physical therapy (8 sessions completed),
            NSAIDs (ibuprofen 800mg TID for 6 weeks), and muscle relaxants (cyclobenzaprine 10mg TID).
            Reports only 20% improvement with current regimen.</paragraph>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Current Medications</title>
          <text>
            <list>
              <item>Ibuprofen 800mg TID</item>
              <item>Cyclobenzaprine 10mg TID PRN</item>
              <item>Gabapentin 300mg TID</item>
              <item>Lisinopril 10mg daily (for HTN)</item>
              <item>Metformin 500mg BID (for DM2)</item>
            </list>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Physical Examination</title>
          <text>
            <paragraph>Vital Signs: BP 138/86, HR 78, Temp 98.4F</paragraph>
            <paragraph>General: Alert, oriented, in mild distress due to pain</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Lumbar Spine: Tenderness to palpation L4-S1 paraspinal muscles, left greater than right.
            Decreased range of motion with flexion (30 degrees) and extension (10 degrees).
            Positive straight leg raise on left at 45 degrees. Negative on right.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Neurological: Left L5 dermatomal hypesthesia. EHL weakness 4/5 on left, 5/5 on right.
            DTRs 2+ bilateral knees, 1+ left ankle, 2+ right ankle.</paragraph>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Imaging Review</title>
          <text>
            <paragraph>MRI Lumbar Spine (dated 2 weeks ago): Large left paracentral disc herniation at L4-L5
            with impingement on the left L5 nerve root. Moderate central canal stenosis.
            Degenerative changes at L3-L4 and L5-S1 without significant neural compression.</paragraph>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Assessment</title>
          <text>
            <list>
              <item>Lumbar radiculopathy, left L5 distribution, secondary to L4-L5 disc herniation</item>
              <item>Lumbar disc herniation L4-L5 with nerve root impingement</item>
              <item>Chronic low back pain, worsening despite conservative management</item>
              <item>Failed conservative therapy</item>
            </list>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
      <component>
        <section>
          <title>Plan</title>
          <text>
            <paragraph>1. Proceed with left L4-L5 transforaminal epidural steroid injection under fluoroscopic guidance
            for diagnostic and therapeutic purposes. Medical necessity established by failed conservative therapy
            and MRI-confirmed pathology correlating with clinical presentation.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>2. Discussed risks, benefits, and alternatives of the procedure. Patient verbalized understanding
            and wishes to proceed. Written consent obtained.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3. Continue gabapentin, may increase to 400mg TID if tolerated.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>4. Follow-up in 2-4 weeks post-procedure to assess response.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>5. If inadequate relief after injection series, will discuss surgical referral.</paragraph>
          </text>
        </section>
      </component>
    </structuredBody>
  </component>
</ClinicalDocument>
